JOSHUA WARD

Technical Lead Software Engineer

Morgantown, WV



I am a full stack software engineer. I have seen nearly all aspects of the software development lifecycle. I've fulfilled front and back end development roles, architected microservices solutions, built critical developer tools and environments, created DevOps pipelines, and written technical documentation to teach others how to do the same. At this early stage in my career, I have served as a technical lead for multiple projects and have fulfilled other minor leadership roles as well. Aside from leadership roles, being a team player is always important and I have had no issue falling in line, working with teammates, and adding meaningful contributions to every team I have been a part of. I have an insatiable passion for technology and I'm not afraid to step outside of my comfort zone.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer III (Technical Lead)

Leidos | 2019 - Present

Serving as the Technical Lead Engineer of a team building a Platform as a Service. This position has been heavily focused on developer tooling, DevOps, and building/deploying microservices.

- Responsible for leading the development of the PaaS reference implementation.
- Have pioneered some of the work related to container orchestration within the Leidos Morgantown office, including work with Kubernetes, Helm, Docker, and Skaffold.
- Have pioneered some of the work related to cloud infrastructure provisioning and continuous delivery within the Leidos Morgantown office, including work with Terraform/Terragrunt, Ansible, and Rancher/Fleet.
- Have worked with other notable tools and technologies such as Apache Kafka, Apache NiFi, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Prometheus, Grafana, and Istio among others.
- Have worked with multiple cloud platforms including AWS/GovCloud, and GCP.
- Built a custom CLI (in my free time) that is now used by many developers leveraging our PaaS to streamline their local development experience.
- Have built and automated repeatable development environments (Docker, Vagrant, AWS Workspaces) that were provisioned using the aforementioned CLI.
- Hosted live training sessions for our PaaS leveraging the aforementioned development environments to streamline the process and ease the learning curve for new developers.
- Additionally serving as a Solution Architect for domain teams looking to modernize. Requires a deep understanding of modern tech stacks in order to consult effectively.

Software Engineer I Leidos | 2017 - 2019

Served as a developer for multiple web application products. This position was primarily focused on both front and back end development using JavaScript and Java.

- Fulfilled development roles on the front end using JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Polymer, and React among other libraries.
- Fulfilled development roles on the back end using Java and RxJava among other libraries.

Graduate Teaching Assistant

West Virginia University | 2016 - 2017

Taught a computer engineering lab focused on x86 assembly language and interfacing with hardware.

- Demonstrated, taught, and graded a junior/senior level computer engineering lab.
- Held office hours to help students with both lab and course work.
- Graded technical lab reports.

Graduate Research Assistant

West Virginia University | 2015 - 2016

Worked with the West Virginia State Police Internet Crimes Against Children Unit (WVSP ICAC) as a Java developer and database administrator.

- Worked with a team using the Agile software development process.
- Had to adapt and learn new technology quickly.
- Worked with AngularJS, Apache Tomcat, Apache NiFi, Docker, MySQL, MongoDB, MVC concepts, and the Spring framework.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

West Virginia University | 2014 - 2015

Worked in the Biometrics Research Department where students operated equipment for biometric collections and wrote scripts to help automate the process.

- Took volunteers through different biometric collections including hand geometry, iris scans, fingerprints, and voice recordings among others.
- Wrote scripts to automate parts of the collection process.

EDUCATION

MSc Electrical Engineering

West Virginia University

2015 - 2017

BSc Computer Engineering

West Virginia University

2010 - 2015

SKILLS

Technical

Java

JavaScript

TypeScript

Golang

Python

Bash

Ansible

Vagrant

Docker

Kubernetes

Helm

Skaffold

Terraform

AWS

Rancher

Apache Kafka

Apache NiFi

Jenkins

Prometheus/Grafana

Istio

Hugo

Professional

Effective communication

Leadership

Strong problem solver

INTERESTS

Technology

Video Games

Soccer

Snowboarding



